如果你参战了
If you go to war,
必将遭受可怕的不幸
you are destined for great and unfortunate things.
我将拔营北进 向阿尔卑斯山进军
I would press north, towards the Alps.
让我们的人四散而去
Let's see our people to the winds.
我们可以从南边进攻
We could press attack from the South.
庞培可以阻止
Pompey could stay Spartacus
斯巴达克斯遁入山中逃跑
from gaining the mountains and slipping from grasp.
下次我就不会这么温柔了
I will not be as gentle next time.
她跑到叛贼的队伍里了
She has moved to join rebellion?
拿提比略的性命来换五百条人命
Five hundred of your men for Tiberius' life
现在这小子毫无价值
The boy holds no value now.
克拉苏会如约交易的
Crassus will yet honor trade.
只要他得到另一样他所渴望的东西
If you give him something else his heart desires.
准备行军
Prepare the men for march.
我要大举进攻斯巴达克斯
I would press towards Spartacus
要他死无葬身之地
and see him to deserved end.
《斯巴达克斯：诅咒者之战》
《伟大胜利》
带话给你这样的奴隶主 立刻释放奴隶
Spread word to your kind to strike shackle from their slaves.
否则他们的宅子就跟你的一样
Or see their houses follow yours
遍地鲜血和死尸
in blood and death.
你是谁
Who are you?
我就是斯巴达克斯
I am Spartacus.
又一座宅子遭袭
Another villa set upon.
总共有几座了
What number holds total?
这几天来 就有六座了
Six in half as many days.
我就是斯巴达克斯
I am Spartacus.
其袭击之迅猛 堪比战神
He lays assault with swiftness to rival winged Mars.
斯巴达克斯只是个普通人
Spartacus stands but mortal man.
凭借我军的装备
I have yet held privilege of one that
才可以做到日行千里
could span distant ground within single breath.
你认为情报是假的
You believe reports false?
我认为他是用计谋
I believe he lays strategy,
目的是迷惑庞培
to set Pompey to confusion,
让他跟着斯巴达克斯的影子乱追
chasing veiled spectre of the man himself.
镇压斯巴达克斯是我们的任务 与庞培无关
We were charged with bringing spartacus to heel, not Pompey.
如果让色雷斯人跑到山的那边
If the Thracian slips beyond the mountain,
败者之名就会落到我们头上
burden of defeat shall rest upon our shoulders.
还有那些在战争中死去的人
And those that have given life towards campaign.
提比略牺牲的那个叛贼营地
There was nothing save cooling embers
已经人去营空 只剩熄灭的篝火
in the rebel camp where Tiberius met his end.
我已经派出斥候去侦察
Forward scouts are yet to have set eyes
斯巴达克斯的动向了
upon Spartacus and his army.
再派
See efforts doubled.
我要尽快逼迫色雷斯人
I would press the Thracian upon field of battle
与我军决战
at soonest opportunity.
我要亲眼看到
And gaze into his eyes
他的眼里永远失去活力和希望
as life and hope forever drain from them.
卢戈 交给你了
Lugo. See it done.
我多少次惊叹于
Many times have I marveled at
你那狂热脑瓜子想出的疯狂计划
mad scheme sprung from fevered mind.
但跟这次相比都是小巫见大巫
Yet one you now set forth towers above all.
我们已经把庞培引去了北边
We have confounded Pompey to the north,
但克拉苏还是从南面攻过来了
yet Crassus still advances from the south
他的兵力远远超过我们
with overwhelming advantage.
希望只能寄托在战场上
Hope lies only in deciding field of final battle.
你就别空口说大话了
You weave barest tether to the promise of such.
我们争取的时间
It will hold long enough
足够让其他人逃走
for the others to slip from grasp.
但愿如此
I pray it so.
希望我能在阻击克拉苏一战中帮得上忙
And would lend much needed aid in giving Crassus fucking pause.
握住这把剑 就让你来
Grip sword. And have it so.
他们夺走了我的一切
They have taken all from me.
你在即将到来的战斗中还有用武之地
You will yet serve purpose in coming battle.
带领那些无法打仗的人上山去
By seeing those who cannot fight to the mountains.
跟纳西尔一起完成任务
Return to task with Nasir,
收拾行装吧
and prepare for journey.
他与行尸走肉无异
The man is more dead than living.
却还愿意为你的大业牺牲
And yet eager to give life to your cause.
我的大业
My cause?
到现在还认为这与你无关吗
It does yet not stand your own?
我可不想以身殉道
I'm no martyr upon cross,
为了让更多人活下去
that will gladly give my life,
主动献出生命什么的
so that those more deserving may live.
那就别急
Then take pause,
道别之前 先安抚你的心吧
see heart attended in advance of parting.
恍若隔世啊
It seems another life.
那时我还在和克雷斯拥抱亲吻
That I last stood in equal embrace with Crixus.
我们失去的太多了
Much has been taken from us.
很快我们就会面对罗马的大军
Soon we will face the legions of Rome.
我们要让他们以血还血
And we will return bitter favor.
这是你做的
You crafted this?
我们把手绑在上面
We will lash hand to grip.
这样在杀罗马人的时候
So it is not torn from grasp
剑和盾就不会脱离掌握
if called to split Roman flesh.
我不能跟他们一起逃到山里去
I cannot flee to the mountains with the others.
无论命令如何 我都要上场杀敌
Despite command, my place is upon field of battle.
而我要永远陪在你身旁
As mine is forever by your side.
到时间了
The hour is upon us.
我不想离开你
I do not want to leave your arms.
我也不想
Nor I see you from them.
可你必须跟他们一起走
Yet you must go with the others.
跟我走吧
Come with me.
你知道我必须留下
You know I must stay.
这样你们才能到达阿尔卑斯山
That you may reach the mountains,
离开共和国 自由地生活
live free of the Republic beyond them.
没有你 活着有什么意思
There is no life absent your touch.
你以前跟我说过
You once said to me that the gods
诸神派我来拯救你
had sent me to save you.
你说错了
And you were mistaken.
诸神派的人是你
You were the one sent.
而我才是需要被拯救的人
And I in need of saving.
等到这场仗打完了
Would you when the battle is end
如果我…
if I may...
什么
May what?
但愿我们在来生的彼岸相见
Then as you wish upon the shores of after life.
有奥诺玛默斯的陪伴
Oenomaus, keep me accompany
等你再回我的怀抱
till I hold you again.
愿诸神保佑你
May the gods protect you.
打败克拉苏和他的大军
See Crassus and his legion to their end.
您的招术依旧锐不可当 统帅
Your skills remain keen, Imperator.
在对阵携雨之使者前
I would sharpen them to deadly edge,
我要磨炼到锋锐无匹
in advance of facing the Bringer of Rain.
他的表情很安详
He appears at peace.
不是吗
Does he not?
是的 主人
Yes, Dominus.
我熟悉的他不是这样子
It is false image of the boy I knew.
永远是眉头紧锁
Forever of furrowed brow
苦想深思的样子
and pressing concern.
跟他父亲一模一样
A reflection of his father,
不苟言笑
grave of face and disposition.
他以前不是这样 对吧
He was not always so. Was he?
是的 主人 他以前不是
No, Dominus. He was not always so.
岁月磨砺了他 剥夺了单纯的快乐
The passing of years hardens a man to the simple joys of life.
直至磨灭一切 只剩铁石心肠
Until all that is left is a thing of stone,
冷酷无情和坚韧不屈
cold and unforgiving.
我真希望事情不是这个样子
I wish nothing more than journey had set towards different path.
再给我讲讲他是怎么死的
Tell me again of his passing.
那些围观的叛贼奴隶
The rebel crowd were thick of slaves
对释放克拉苏之子感到愤怒
angry for the son of Crassus been set free.
有一个奴隶拿刀冲出人群
One broke from crowd with knife punch ahead
冲到恺撒和提比略的路上
at Caesar and Tiberius way
告诉我 杀他的奴隶什么样
Give voice to slave that robbed him of life.
那人上了年纪
A man long in years.
主人的标记深深地烙进了肉里
With scars of his master etched upon flesh.
要是他早点死
Would that he had been struck from this world,
提比略或许就能活下来了
so that Tiberius may yet be of it.
很抱歉打搅您
Apologies for intrusion.
前方斥候回报
We have received word from forward scouts.
斯巴达克斯的消息吗
Spartacus?
他有一小队人往北边去了
A clutch of his men sighted to the north.
传令下去 拔起营寨
Give order to break encampment
全军出发
and fall to march.
遵命
Imperator.
战争终于要结束了
War at last draws to its end.
这是必然的
As all things must,
不该做的梦 总有醒来的一天
born of man and misplaced desire.
卫兵会带你回到你该去的地方
The guards will see you returned to where you belong.
您还没有问过我为什么要背叛您
You have not asked yet why I turned from you.
答案能使时光倒流吗
Could answer reverse course of time's passing?
能抚平心中最深的伤痛吗
Or erase memory of deepest wound?
不能
No.
但我愿意拿性命
Yet I would give life to gaze upon
换得您的原谅
forgiveness in your eyes again.
这都是我造成的
For all that I have done.
我不会再心软了
If but I could be so moved.
一离开营地 你我就分道而行了
Once beyond camp, you will divide number and path.
这样你们才能瞒过庞培 有机会进山
Better give chance of reaching mountains absent discovery by Pompey.
我觉得如果由你带领我们 机会更大
I would count fortune more assured, were you to lead us.
必须有人挡住克拉苏
Crassus must be given pause.
这样你们才有时间逃走
So that you and the others may slip beyond grasp.
我们会等你 就在山脚下
We will wait for you then, at foot of the mountains.
我不许你这么做
But I would not have it so.
我想怎么做 难道不是我的自由吗
Am I not free, to make own choice?
你总这么说
As you frequently remind.
但别拿生命冒险
Yet do not hazard life,
说不定我能活下来
in hopes that I yet cling to my own.
你不会在和克拉苏的战斗中死去的
You will not fall in battle against Crassus.
你现在还能够预知未来了
You now hold power to pierce future's uncertain veil?
我只是相信
I hold but faith.
相信这个与众不同的男人
In a man like no other.
谢谢 谢谢你这样说
Gratitude. For your words.
还有你的陪伴带给我的安慰
And for what comfort your presence has given.
去吧
Go.
别死在罗马狗手里 贱人
Do not fall to the Romans, you well, cunt.
老娘操翻他们
I fuck them all
再来找你
you will return.
你的任务搞清楚了吗
You are clear of purpose?
再清楚不过了
Never more so.
纳西尔和我不跟他们一起
Yet Nasir and I shall not be among those
往阿尔卑斯山走
striking towards mountains.
我们已经说好了
We have broken words towards subject.
你不能战斗…
You cannot fight
但他找到了方法
He has yet found way,
是我亲手帮的忙
forged by loving hands.
大战在即 休想叫我袖手旁观
Do not ask my own to lay idle in coming battle.
我亲眼看见很多兄弟死去
I have born witness to the fall of many I have called brother.
当年和我一起
You are the last yet living
大闹巴蒂塔斯家的兄弟 只有你还活着
that stood with me when Batiatus' ludus was laid to ruin.
我很荣幸
You honor me,
能和你在决战中再次并肩
by standing again at my side in final conflict.
他们准备好出发了
They are ready to journey.
朋友们
My friends.
我们分别的时候到了
The time of our parting has come.
记住 当我们面对克拉苏的大军时
Know that you will be heavy upon thought
我们最挂念的就是你们
when we face Crassus and his legions.
很多人会死
Many of us will fall.
无论什么谋略和计策
There remains strategy nor deception
都已无法改变这一命运
that can bend course of inevitable fate.
但请记住 我们的热血
Yet know that our blood...
换来的是宝贵的机会
shall purchase needed opportunity
好让你们翻山而去
for you to gain mountain paths.
离开罗马的尖牙利爪
Beyond snapping jaws of Rome
离开带给我们死亡和不幸的血盆大口
that have plagued us with death... ...and misery.
就此分别
Part ways.
自由生活吧
And live free.
感谢你所做的一切
Gratitude. For all you've done.
谢谢 谢谢 斯巴达克斯
Gratitude. Gratitude, Spartacus.
Gratitude. Gratitude Spartacus.
愿诸神护佑你
May the gods bless you.
谢谢
Gratitude...
Gratitude.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
有罗马探子看到我们往山谷南面去了
Roman scouts have laid eyes upon us to the south of the valley!
他们佩戴的是什么徽章
What markings did they bear?
胸前是可怕的公牛
Fearsome bull upon chest.
是克拉苏的人
Crassus.
总算是上钩了
Fucking bait is seized upon.
赶快出发 不要回头
Set upon path, and do not turn from it!
走
Go!
我会祈祷
I shall lend prayer.
希望克拉苏灭亡
Toward the end of Crassus.
斯巴达克斯凯旋
And the triumph of Spartacus.
我已经受够了眼泪和道别
I have had my fill of words and tearful farewells.
我现在要的是
I desire blood,
敌人的鲜血和惨叫
and cries of our enemy.
那我们便去要来吧
Let us make it so.
停
Halt!
弩炮准备
Balistae ready!
没有命令不许妄动
Do not engage unless given command!
预备
Stand ready!
矛
Spear.
我不是来挑衅的
I do not seek quarrel!
只是代克拉苏统帅传达口信
Only to deliver message from Imperator Crassus!
矛
Spear.
有话快说
Break words.
如果说的是废话 别怪我不客气
And pray to your gods I find them of worth.
此情此景你可曾见过
Have you ever witnessed such a thing?
多少颗跳动的心
So many hearts,
即将不可避免地迎接死亡
beating towards inevitable end?
为何叫我过来 克拉苏
Why did you call me here, Crassus?
跟你一样
The same reason you came.
出于好奇
Curiosity.
那你满意了吗
Well has it been satisfying?
我们这对冤家纠缠了许久
We've vexed each other for many months.
彼此都遭受了巨大的伤痛
Both suffering grievous wound upon effort.
却从来没有机会说两句话
Yet have never broken single word.
说与不说又有什么区别
There are none that would hold difference.
也许吧
Perhaps.
但是无论如何 我还是想跟你谈谈
Yet I would stil l have them regardless.
退下
Leave us.
统帅
Imperator
服从命令
Fall to command.
结果显而易见 不是吗
It is a thing known, is it not?
你不可能赢
That you cannot win this conflict.
很多罗马人
A sentiment shared.
都有过同样的想法 最后死于我的剑下
By all the Romans I have killed who held such belief.
我儿子就是其中之一
My son among them.
很抱歉 统帅大人
Apologies Imperator
对于那个杀了克雷斯的罗马战士
I cannot give voice to regret of passing.
我可不能表达哀悼之情
To the soldier that robbed Crixus of life.
高卢人死在战场上
The Gaul died upon field of battle.
提比略却不是
An honor denied Tiberius.
并不是我这样安排的
It is not as I had commanded.
可惜那个被你儿子虐待过的女人
Yet the woman had been rudely treated by his hands,
一心想要复仇
and her own claimed vengeance.
我也深切地体会到丧子之痛
As mine are so moved in memory of my son.
而你对你妻子的…
And yours towards wife no longer
不要以为我们的伤痛可以相提并论
Do not think to place your loss upon equal footing.
你儿子为共和国而战
Your son took up arms for the Republic.
正是共和国夺走了我无辜的妻子
The same one that saw my innocent wife torn from grasp
将她贬为奴隶 害她死去
and condemned to slavery and death.
而现在你还要垂死挣扎 害千万人送死
And now you would lead thousands to join her in futile attempt.
我那些兄弟姐妹的命运
Whatever happens to my people
都是自己选择的
it happens because we choose for it.
我们自己决定命运 不由你
We decide our fates. Not you.
不由罗马
Not the Romans.
也不由天上的诸神
Not even the gods.
你们选择的不过是灭亡的时间和地点
You choose but time and place of journey's end.
死于剑下
Better to fall by the sword
好过死在主人的鞭下
than by the master's lash.
这能抚平你的伤痛吗
And will it balm festering wound?
如果携雨之使者再次创造奇迹
If the Bringer of Rain heralds miracle
击败克拉苏和他的军团
and defeats Crassus and his legions,
他会不会离开共和国呢
will he withdraw from the Republic?
为他所带来的公正
Content that he's brought those
而感到心满意足
who so injured him to justice?
根本没有公正可言
There is no justice.
这个世上没有
Not in this world.
终于
At last.
我们也有意见一致的时候
A thing we agree upon.
下一次见面 我必定要你的命
When we again meet, I will kill you.
不可能 你只能试试
No. You are going to try.
这就是自由人的权利
It is all a free man can do.
你可不能相信斯巴达克斯的话
You cannot place trust in the words of Spartacus.
他有什么理由在这件事情上骗我
What reason would he have to twist tongue upon subject?
我可不会假装知道
I do not pretend to know lay
奴隶的脑子在想什么
of a savage's fucking thoughts.
再说一次
Tell me again.
杀死提比略的凶手到底是谁
What hand struck Tiberius from this life?
我说过了 是个上了年纪的男人…
One belonging to a man long in years, as I have said
斯巴达克斯说是个女人
Spartacus spoke of a woman.
而且是为了复仇
Moved by vengeance.
他无非是企图用谎言离间我们
He but attempts to turn us against each other with plotted lie.
这话若有半分虚假 我决不轻饶
The threat of ruin carries upon such deceit, if so embraced.
只有道出真相
Yet only in the breaking of truth
才有可能得到原谅
swells hope of forgiveness.
对提比略下手的人是我
It was my hand that moved against Tiberius,
是我亲手杀了他
and saw him from this world.
我待你太残酷吗
Was my touch so cruel?
以至于你杀死我高贵的儿子 来伤透我的心
That you would strike at heart through noble son?
快说
Speak!
趁你的喉咙还没有断掉
While you yet have throat to give voice!
你岂能怪罪受害者
You place blame upon victim!
你那臭小子真是高贵 竟然强奸了她
Your "Noble" Fucking son forced himself inside her.
他恶行累累 罪有应得
One of many acts that lead to deserved fate.
还说谎
More lies!
他说的是真的
It is the truth!
十一抽杀刑毕后
His love for you turned to hate
提比略对您由爱转恨
in the wake of the decimation.
他用唯一可行的方式报复了您
And he struck at you the only way he could.
他知道只有这样才能伤您最深
One he knew would inflict deepest wound.
你怎么不早跟我说
Why did you not tell me?
我在米利亚峰曾想说出来
I made attempt, upon Melia Ridge.
他毕竟是我心爱的儿子
There is no misstep that would see father
无论犯下什么错 都是可以原谅的
withhold forgiveness from treasured son.
我们不想再给你增添无谓的痛苦 马科斯
We did not wish to cause you further pain absent reason, Marcus.
所以才没有说出真相
The cause of withholding truth.
下去吧
Leave us.
有其父必有其子
A son is but reflection of the father.
难道我是这样的人吗
Is this how I stand?
扭曲而怪异
Twisted and grotesque?!
您从来没有变过
You stand as you always have.
正直无私 恪尽职守
A good man. That does what he must.
抱歉
Apologies.
让你受了这么多苦
Apologies for all you've suffered.
等剿灭斯巴达克斯 一切都会结束
Know that it shall end when Spartacus falls.
战争中的种种不幸
And unfortunate events of war
必将烟消云散
trod path of distant memory.
(卡拉布利亚)
(色雷斯)
担子不轻啊
It is heavy burden.
眼看战争接近尾声 掂量代价有多沉重
Gaze at war's end. And weigh bitter cost of it.
你不相信我们能打败克拉苏
You do not believe that we can defeat Crassus?
你总能变不可能为可能
You are forever conjuring the impossible.
这最后一把我也不会赌别人赢
And I would not wager against you in final gambit.
但局势不太乐观啊
Yet odds are not of a favor.
是啊 的确不乐观
No. They are not.
我本打算请你喝一杯快活快活
I would offer drink to lift spirits,
但最近我已经戒了酒
but I have turned from it of late.
我注意到了
A thing not escaping notice.
当那颗纯洁的心占据我的身心
I too turned from wild pursuits.
我也不再放荡不羁
When possessed by purest heart.
你是说你的妻子
You speak of your wife?
我们第一次相拥而睡时
When we first lay together,
她说诸神托梦给她 以传达神谕
she told of how the gods delivered oracle in her dreams.
预言我不会再爱上别的女人
And foretold that I would never love another woman.
预言成真了吗
Did prophecy hold true?
我在别人那里找到过安慰
I found comfort in others.
但心中总有空虚 永远无法填满
Yet there's an emptiness that can never be filled.
那里原是心脏跳动的地方
A void left where heart once beat,
在苏拉离开我的时候掏空了
when Sura was taken from me.
你曾经问过我胜利该如何定义
You once questioned how victory can be defined.
我认为罗马人的死就是胜利
I thought answer held in Roman deaths.
现在不这么想了吗
A position no longer taken?
生命 而不是罗马人的死
Life is what defines it.
定义了何为胜利
Not the death of Romans.
不是我们的命 也不是兄弟们的命
Nor ours, nor those that follow us into battle.
而是希贝儿的命
But the life of Sibyl.
莱塔的命 那对母子的命
Of Laeta, the mother and her child,
还有许许多多人的命
so many others.
他们都是苏拉
They are all Sura.
我要他们活下去
And I would see them live.
这样的大业 即便是我也愿意接受
A cause even I can embrace.
如果我们要其他人逃脱克拉苏的魔掌
If we are to give the others any chance against Crassus,
你仅仅接受是不够的
you must do more than embrace it.
你必须领导
You must lead.
别老调重弹了 斯巴达克斯
An old argument, Spartacus.
现在必须说清楚
One that must now stand settled.
要是你不能负起应有的责任 我是做不来的
I cannot do this without you assuming rightful position.
只有你能扛起这副担子
One that there is none more deserving of.
你要我做什么
What would you have me do?
不可能的事
The impossible.
士兵都就位了
The men stand ready?
是的 统帅
They do, Imperator.
谢谢
Gratitude.
为你的忠诚效力
For loyal service.
斯巴达克斯是傻瓜
Spartacus stands the fool,
带这么点人对抗我们的大军
to face our legions with so few.
他这人一言难以蔽之
He has proven himself many things.
但傻瓜一词不在其中
A fool not among them.
他们真是人山人海
They stand an ocean.
就和克雷斯被吞没时一样
As when Crixus was swept from the shores of the living.
他们是给我们提供机会
They but offer opportunity.
好让我们畅游在罗马人的血海之中
To swim in a sea of Roman blood.
可怕的不幸
Great and unfortunate things.
你这话是什么意思
What meaning do words carry?
是警告 是一位心爱的妻子
A warning, given voice by loving wife.
对即将战死的丈夫说的
To a man who no longer exists.
克拉苏即将下令开战
Soon Crassus will give command!
我们要与他的大军一决雌雄
And we shall face his legions in open battle!
我们面对的是强大的敌人
We stand in the shadow of greater might!
他们所代表的共和国的阴影笼罩着
As their Republic cast across the lives of every man...
每一个男人 女人和孩子
every woman... And every child...
要我们在阴影中苟且偷生
condemned to the darkness of slavery!
他们害我们受苦受难
Forced to toil and suffer,
好让那些达官贵人
so that those of coin and position
过上穷奢极欲的生活
can see their fortunes grow beyond need or purpose!
我们来告诉他们
Let us teach them,
人人生而平等
that all who draw breath are of equal worth!
那些企图践踏个人意志
And that those that seek to place heel
镇压人民的无知权贵
upon the throat of liberty...
必将倒在自由的怒吼声中
Will fall to the cry of freedom!
此战要斩尽杀绝 不可心慈手软
No wounded enemy is to be blessed with merciful passing!
我要杀鸡儆猴 让共和国的敌人
I would make example of all those who dare raise
引以为戒
hand against the glory of Rome!
投石器和弩炮准备
Raise ballistae and catapults.
装弹
Go!
点火
Ignite!
准备 放
Ready! Release!
吹进军号
Sound advance!
一举清缴叛贼
And see Rebellion distant memory!
前进
Advance!
原地待命
Take position!
稳住
Hold...
Hold!
弓箭手
Archers!
射
Now!
这野蛮人真是诡计多端
The savage yet proves resourceful.
他不过是螳臂当车
He but delays coming tide with grains of sand.
发号令 摆龟甲阵
Give signal to form testudo!
他们果然中计了
They fall to predicted maneuver.
那就打他们个措手不及
Let us show them one unexpected.
上
Now!
准备投石器和弩炮
Raise command for ballistae and catapults!
连我军将士一起杀吗
You would rain death upon our own men?
我要打赢这场仗
I would end this fucking war!
别停下脚步
Do not turn from advance!
往前冲
Press forward!
我操你娘
还是统帅棋高一着 奴隶大军完蛋了
The slaves fall to superior strategy and tactic.
我们也打死了不少罗马士兵
As do Romans beneath our command.
这是不幸的损失
An unfortunate loss.
不过完全可以接受
Yet one gladly accepted,
这都是为了剿灭斯巴达克斯…
to bring Spartacus to his end
骑兵来了
Riders approaching!
向后转
About face!
调转弩炮的方向 快
Turn ballistae! Quickly!
你去那边 保护左翼
You there! Defend the left flank!
恺撒 快去后方领军
Caesar! Take command of rear position!
千万不可乱了阵脚
Do not let them fall to confusion!
我们必须撤退
We must withdraw!
不 撤退就正中他下怀了
No! That is what he expects!
吹号角 前进
Sound horn and advance!
卡斯特斯
Castus!
如果我是你该有多好
Would that I had been you...
哪怕就一天
for but a day.
艾力冈
Agron!
你这路要撑住
Shore your flank!
别让他们包围我们
Do not let them close upon us!
纳西尔
Nasir!
妮维雅 支援甘尼克斯
Naevia! Aid Gannicus!
快去
Move!
我们走
Come!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
统帅
Imperator!
保护统帅
Protect the Imperator!
克拉苏
Crassus!
真是光荣的一天
It is a glorious day!
能杀这么多罗马人
To have so many Romans to kill!
只有杀了那个人才有意义
It is but one life that holds meaning.
你负责战场
Draw attention upon field.
我去讨命
I shall claim it.
保持阵型
Hold the line!
快去拿双耳罐 朝他们扔过去
Seize amphoras and see them to purpose!
恺撒
Caesar!
快找医官来
Send for the medicus!
我不需要疗伤
I need no soothing balm.
我要回战场杀叛贼
Only to return to field with rebel blood hot upon face.
您可要长远考虑
Do not place yourself at further risk.
如果您倒下了 斯巴达克斯就占据上风
If you fall, spartacus would gain advantage
我早就想跟你真刀真枪干一场
I have longed to meet you in true contest.
我也早就想把你该死的脑袋
As I have longed to see your head
给砍下来了
parted from fucking neck.
萨克莎
Saxa!
我终于又
躺在你怀里了
我承诺过
I made promise.
下一次见面
That time next we met...
我必取你性命
I would have your life.
来吧
Come then.
看你有没有这本事
And attempt to take it.
列阵
Formation!
这剑不属于你 奴隶
This does not belong to you, slave.
不
No!
轮换
Rotate!
停
Hold!
且慢
Halt!
真希望你生为罗马人
Would that you had been born a Roman.
为我效力
And had stood beside me.
命运待我不薄
I bless the fates...
没有如你所愿
that it was not so.
艾力冈
Agron!
给我剑
Give me a sword...
统帅
Imperator
跟着我 夺回山丘
Fall by my side and retake hill!
扫荡附近的山丘
Sweep surrounding hills!
遵命
Imperator!
诸神又帮了斯巴达克斯
The gods once more aid Spartacus
让他逃出我们的手心
in slipping from fucking grasp.
他遍体鳞伤
He weeps from a thousand wounds.
就算还没死
And if heart yet beats,
也活不了多久
it shall cease at briefest passing
还有很多跟随他造反的人
There are many who have followed mad cause
没有断气
that still cling to fading life.
那就在亚壁古道杀鸡儆猴
See them to promised example upon Appian Way.
要所有胆敢反抗罗马的奴隶都知道
And let all slaves, upon road to Mother Rome know reward
与主人作对是什么下场
for turning hand against master.
死得真不光彩
Ignoble end.
对于昔日竞技场的传奇战神而言
For a legend that once stood a god of the arena.
传奇不过是有血有肉的美梦而已
Legends are but bone and meat of dreams.
在现实的烈日下唯有腐烂一途
Rotting in the harsh sun of reality.
真不忍心看
It is hard sight.
曾经深受宠爱的人也在受刑之列
To see one so loved among the damned.
众所周知她也是叛贼的一员
She was known to be of the rebellion.
我有心饶恕
I have forgiven reason.
但别无选择
Yet do what I must.
庞培
Pompey.
看到老朋友安然无恙 真是谢天谢地
Praise the gods to find you well old friend.
我还担心我在北边剿匪时
I'd feared that Spartacus and his Rebels
斯巴达克斯及其叛众把你给灭了呢
had overrun you before I routed him in the north.
北边
The north?
他率军剿灭了逃往山中的叛贼
He came upon rebel army attempting to gain the mountains.
消息已经送往罗马
Dispatch has already been sent to Rome,
认定庞培有功
naming Pompey victor
剿灭了你没能镇压的敌人
against enemy you could not quell.
功劳不是你的
You claim false laurels.
斯巴达克斯是…
Spartacus was defeated
在北边覆没 多亏了勇猛的庞培
in the north. By valiant Pompey,
伊伯利亚的英雄
hero of Hispania.
承蒙夸赞
You honor me.
我夸赞的是罗马的胜利
I but honor Rome.
各位同心协力 罗马必能繁荣昌盛
And those of like mind, that would see it flourish.
英雄所见略同
Then we are one in such regard.
我们为你接风洗尘
Let us break meal on your return.
费了千辛万苦
After all that we have suffered,
你就让庞培抢走了胜利果实
you allow Pompey to snatch triumph from deserving hands?
我们表态支持 便可以拉拢他
Supporting claim he will be made ally.
我们将成为强大的三巨头
We shall stand fearsome triumvirate,
强大到足以影响历史的进程
with means to bend the course of history.
你总是说未来的事情
You forever speak of the future.
过去已经无法改变
The past cannot be altered.
当下只有遗憾与损失
The present holds but regret and loss.
唯有未来 可以抚慰人心的伤痛
It is only in the days to come that a man may find solace.
让回忆烟消云散
When memory fades.
甘尼克斯 甘尼克斯
Gannicus! Gannicus! Gannicus!...
他还活着
He yet lives.
我们到阿尔卑斯山了
We've gained the mountains.
我们在等你 说好了的
We waited for you, as promised.
都没事吗
All safe?
庞培袭击了另一路人
Pompey set upon other half.
很多人死了
Many were lost.
我们必须带他上山了
We must see him to mountain path,
否则我们也会被发现
before we too are discovered.
别动
Stay hand.
我要休息一会儿
I would rest awhile.
我们不能留在这里
We cannot stay here.
你们当然不能
No, you cannot.
我也不能跟你们走了
Nor can I follow.
斯巴达克斯 斯巴达克斯
Spartacus... Spartacus.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
这不是我的名字
That is not my name.
我终于能再一次听见
I shall finally hear it again.
心爱的妻子呼唤我的名字
Given voice by loving wife...
发出渴望已久的问候
in greeting longed for...
不要流泪
Do not shed tear.
没有比这更伟大的胜利了
There is no greater victory...
死的时候
than to fall from this world...
是自由之身
a free man.
终有一日 罗马将不复存在
One day Rome shall fade and crumble.
但所有追求自由的人
Yet you shall always be remembered.
都将永远把你铭记于心
In the hearts of all who yearn for freedom.